Finding Aid for Ecology Center of Ann Arbor records, 1969-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Topical Files
  - 1972-2010, mainly 1988-2005
    - Grants, 1972-1973; 1987-2002
      - United States Environmental Protection Agency, 1992-2001
        - Pollution Prevention in the Automobile Manufacturing and Metal Finishing Sectors: Nationwide Diffusion of Proven Technologies through a Multi-Stakeholder Approach, 1995 (Box 25)
        - ReBicycle Project, 1997-1999 (Box 25)
        - Sustainable Communities Environmental Education Project, 1995-1996 (Box 25)
      - W. Alton Jones Foundation, 1995-2001 (Box 26)
        (for The Great Lakes Environmental Health Campaign)
      - W.K. Kellog Foundation, 1988-1996
        - Citizen Action for Pollution Prevention Project, 1993-1996 (Box 26)
        - Groundwater Education in Michigan, 1989-1994
          - GEE-WOW! Program Grant, 1988-1989 (Box 26)
            (includes Groundwater Education on Wheels: Programs and Displays in Groundwater Education and Environmental Awareness for Students -- A Request for Funding)
          - Letters of Recommendation, 1990; 1994 (Box 26)
          - Project Reports, 1989-1993 (Box 26)
      - Washtenaw County Master Gardener Alumni Association, 2001-2002 (Box 26)
        (for Compostability: Teaching Kids the Hows & Whys of Composting Program)
      - WEDO, 1995-1996 (Box 26)
        (for The Environmental Connection: The Rising Rates of Breast Cancer, Reproductive Disorders and Children's Disease Conference)
    - Land Preservation, 1999-2003
      - Ann Arbor Parks Department-Park Repair and Restoration Millage, 2002-2003 (Box 26)
      - Botsford Recreational Preserve, 2001 (Box 26)
        (Letter to the Ecology Center Director requesting support in the preservation of the Botsford Recreational Preserve)
      - Greenbelt District Program
        - Ann Arbor Greenbelt Activity Report, 2006 (Box 26)
        - Implementation of the Ann Arbor Greenbelt District Program, 2005 (Box 26)
        - Proposal for: City of Ann Arbor Greenbelt District Program Implementation Consulting Services, 2004 (Box 26)
      - Mallets Creek Restoration Project, 1999-2000
        - Mallets Creek Restoration Plan: Executive Summary and Mallets Creek Management Plan, 2000 (Box 26)
        - Meetings and Correspondence, 1999 (Box 26)
        - Restoring a Community Resource: The Mallets Creek Report, 1999 (Box 26)
    - Land Use, 1995-2004
      - Broadway Village at Lower Town Development Program, 2002-2003 (Box 26)
      - Colt Farms Zoning, 2001 (Box 26)
      - Ecology Center Land Use Program, 2001 (Box 26)
      - Ecology Center Position on Infill and Sprawl Developments, 1999 (Box 26)
      - Huron Land Use Alliance/Coalition, 1995-1997 (Box 26)
      - Sprawl / Purchase Development Rights (PDR), 2001-2002 (Box 26)
      - Transfer of Development Rights, 2001 (Box 26)
      - Washtenaw County Comprehensive Plan, 2002-2004
        - A Comprehensive Plan for Washtenaw County Draft, 2004 (Box 26)
        - Meetings and Correspondence, 2001-2004 (Box 26)
          (2001 Washtenaw County Resource Assessment)
    - Lawsuit Against Governor John Engler Regarding Executive Order 1991-31, 1991-1993 (Box 26)
      (includes Michigan Environmental Report; Vol. 9, No. 3, May-June 1991)
    - Miscellaneous Topical Files, 1986-2010
      - Chelsea Area Regional Plan, 2000 (Box 26)
      - Department of Natural Resources (DNR), 1986-1991
        - Reorganization, 1991 (Box 26)
          (includes Managing Michigan's Natural Resources: A Historical Overview of the Department of Natural Resources)
        - David Hales, 1986-1989
          - DNR-Role in SARA Title III, 1988-1989 (Box 26)
          - Paper and Interview, 1986-1988 (Box 26)
      - Green Jobs Bond, 2005 (Box 26)
      - Holcim, 2002 (Box 26)
        (Letter to Ecology Center Director regarding permit application for expansion of non-hazardous fuels at Dundee manufacturing plant)
      - Lake Michigan Federation Case Study, 1995-1996 (Box 26)
        (includes Pollution Prevention and Chemical Safety: A Local Case Study)
      - Toxic Toys, 2008-2010 (Box 26)
        (news articles regarding the Ecology Center's involvement in the research of toxic toys)
    - Natural Areas / Natural Washtenaw Campaign, 2000
      - Bulk Permit (Box 27)
      - Campaign Materials (Box 27)
      - Correspondence (Box 27)
      - Endorsement Materials (Box 27)
      - Information on Letters to Editor (Box 27)
      - Mailing Information (Box 27)
      - Proposal Language and Ordinance No. 128 (Box 27)
      - Strategy, Timelines, and Meeting Notes (Box 27)
      - Voting Information by Precinct and Campaign Expenses (Box 27)
    - People for Parks, 1997-2000
      - Ann Arbor Parks Millage, 1997-2000 (Box 27)
      - Promotional Materials (Box 27)
    - Recycle Ann Arbor (RAA), 1990-2006
      - Board of Directors -- Meetings and Administrative Documents
        - 1995 (Box 27)
        - 1996 (Box 27)
        - 1997 (Box 27)
        - 1998 (Box 27)
        - 1999 (Box 27)
        - 2000 (Box 27)
        - 2001 (Box 27)
        - 2002 (Box 27)
        - Miscellaneous, 1990-2000 (Box 27)
      - City of Ann Arbor RFT #432: Residential Recycling Collection Services, 1998 (Box 27)
      - Comprehensive Drop-Off Station, 1995 (Box 27)
      - En-House -- Green Buildings Initiative, 1997-1998 (Box 27)
      - Evaluation Committee, 1990-1992 (Box 27)
      - Genesee County Recycling Outreach Campaign, 2000-2006
        - Correspondence and Administrative Documents, 2000-2006 (Box 27)
        - Final Report -- Part I: Determination of Genesee County Recycling Rate; Part II: Recommendations for Increasing Recycling, 2005 (Box 27)
        - Genesee County Solid Waste Management Plan, 2000-2005; 2002 (Box 27)
      - Legal Documents, 1990-1992 (Box 27)
      - Recycle Jackson, 2004 (Box 27)
      - Recycle West, 1995-2004 (Box 27)
      - Report to Recycle Ann Arbor: A Study of Some Aspects of the Feasibility of Establishing a Reuse Business, 1994 (Box 27)
      - Solid Waste Collection and Disposal Contract, 1991 (Box 28)
      - Strategic Planning, 1993 (Box 28)
      - Union Organization Committee, 1991-1992 (Box 28)
      - Waste Management, Inc. 2001 Annual Report (Box 28)
    - Toronto Trash, 1996-2003; 2010
      - July 2003 U.S. Congressional Hearing, 2003 (Box 28)
      - No Waste Campaign, 1996-2000 (Box 28)
      - Toronto, 2000; 1999-2002 (Box 28)
      - Toronto Waste Diversion Task Force 2010 Report, 2010 (Box 28)
    - Transportation, 1994-2003
      - Bicycle Recycle Project, 1994; 1997-1998 (Box 28)
        (a.k.a. ReBicycle a.k.a. Bicycle Reuse)
      - Clean Cities Program, 1997-2000 (Box 28)
      - SEMCOG/MDOT 2025, Transportation Plan Public Meeting, 2001 (Box 28)
      - Sustainable Transportation, 2001-2003 (Box 28)
    - Washtenaw Purchase Development Rights (PDR), 1994-2001
      - Agricultural Preservation Fund, 2001 (Box 28)
      - Campaign Plan, 1993; 1998 (Box 28)
      - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 28)
      - Endorsements, 1998 (Box 28)
      - Event Handouts, 1998 (Box 28)
      - Farmers for Farmland Preservation, 1998 (Box 28)
      - Legal and Billing Documents, 1997-1999 (Box 28)
      - Master Copies and Forms, 1998 (Box 28)
      - PDR Initiative, 1994-1998 (Box 28)
      - Polling Washtenaw, 1996-1998 (Box 28)
      - Press Releases, 1998 (Box 28)
      - Proposal 1 Campaign Financial Reports, 1998 (Box 28)
      - Purchase Development Rights, 1998 (Box 28)
      - Purchase Development Rights Revision Committee Notebook, 1998; 2003-2004 (Box 28)
      - Save Our Land Save Our Future (SOLSOF), 1996-1998
        - Campaign Materials, 1996-1998 (Box 28)
        - Promotional Materials (Box 28)
      - Washtenaw Ballot Measure, 1997-1998
        - Ordinance, 1997-1998 (Box 29)
        - Message Work, 1998 (Box 29)
          (includes Sierra Club Huron Valley Group Newsletter, May-June 1998 Vol. XXI, No. 3)
      - Washtenaw Citizens for Responsible Growth-Flyers and Fact Sheets, 1998 (Box 29)
      - Washtenaw County Agricultural Lands and Open Space Preservation Plan, 1997 (Box 29)
        (includes Executive Summary of the Final Report)
      - Washtenaw County Agricultural Project, 1995-1997 (Box 29)
    - Waste, 1988-2005
      - Central Wayne Incinerators, 1997-1998; 2001-2002 (Box 29)
      - Detroit Incinerators, 1996; 2001-2005 (Box 29)
      - Wayne County Solid Waste Plan, 2000-2001 (Box 29)
        (Heritage Papers Letter to the Editor)
      - Proposed Waste Reduction and Recycling Ordinance, 1988-1989 (Box 29)
        (includes Final Report Preliminary Analysis: Proposed Waste Reduction and Recycling Ordinance for The City of Ann Arbor)
      - Solid Waste Surcharge, 2003-2004 (Box 29)
      - Stop the Burn Coalition, 2001-2003 (Box 29)
      - Ypsilanti Community Utilities Authority Biosolids Disposal Program, 2001 (Box 29)
        (Letter to the Board of Commissioners)
    - Wetlands, 1999-2003
      - Delcor Homes in Scio Township, 2000 (Box 29)
        (Request to build culvert in wetlands area)
      - Ford Lake Environmental Protection Group, 2001 (Box 29)
        (Cliff's Landing steel seawall built without permit)
      - Friends of Pickerel Lake, 2001 (Box 29)
      - People for Local Ordinances, 2001 (Box 29)
      - Why Work to Protect the River System?, circa, 1999
        - Photos (Box 29)
          (of environmentally sound storm water management practices, courtesy of Peter Pollack Design)
        - Presentation, circa 1999 (Box 29)
      - Woodland Meadows Expansion, 2003 (Box 29)
- Printed Materials and Publicity
  The Printed Materials and Publicity series is comprised of newsletters, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, collected bound materials, and works published by the Ecology Center. The extensive newspaper clippings are arranged chronologically. There are also clippings scattered throughout the topical files. The three newsletters included in this collection are subject-specific and are issued on an irregular basis. Collected bound materials pertain to events and solid waste management, such as the Remedial Action Plan for the City of Ann Arbor Landfill. Other printed materials include works published by the Ecology Center, such as the Footloose in Washtenaw walking guide and Ann Arbor Alive.
  - Newsletters
    - Michigan Toxics Watch, 1990-1991 (Box 16)
    - Nonprofit Energy News, 1988-1990 (Box 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1995; 21 folders (Box 16)
  - Flyers, Pamphlets, and Mailings, 1989-1996; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Press Releases, 1981-1989; 6 folders (Box 16)
  - Publications
    - Ann Arbor Alive: the Ecology of a City (Box 16)
    - A Consumers' Guide to Lawn and Tree Care (Box 16)
    - Footloose in Washtenaw: a revised and expanded walkers' guide to Washtenaw County (Box 16)
    - Guarding Michigan's Most Vulnerable: Making Michigan a Leader in Protecting Children from Environmental Pollution, 2002 (Box 16)
    - The Goddamn Report: comparative organizational analysis of eight ecology centers (Box 16)
    - Michigan Household Hazardous Substance Handbook (Box 16)
    - Toxics in My Home? You Bet!: curriculum on household toxics for grades 9-12 (Box 16)
    - Disposing of Your Hazardous Household Waste, 1987 (Box 16)
    - Paper Recycling for Recyclers, 1980 (Box 16)
    - So Much Promise, So Little Progress: An Evaluation of the State of Michigan/Auto Industry Great Lakes Pollution Prevention Initiative, 1993 (Box 16)
  - Recycling Promotions, 1981-1986; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Collected Bound Materials
    - Events
      - Designing Healthy Livable Communities -- Conference Program, 2004 (Box 30)
      - League of Conservation Voters Education Fund -- 1996 Grassroots Leadership Summit (Box 30)
      - League of Conservation Voters Education Fund --List Enhancement Project
        - 1999 (Box 30)
        - 2000 (Box 30)
      - Mesquite III (in Baltimore) -- Earth Share / Environmental Federations Campaign Report, 1999 (Box 30)
      - Out of Harm's Way: Preventing Toxic Threats to Child Development in Michigan -- Conference Materials for Health Professionals, 2005 (Box 30)
      - Workshop on the Transition to Virtual Elimination: Dioxins and Furans as a Case Study -- Workshop Briefing Book, 1995 (Box 30)
    - Remedial Action Plan for the City of Ann Arbor Landfill
      - City of Ann Arbor Landfill Feasibility Study/Remedial Action Plan for the Treatment of Impacted Off-Site Groundwater, 1996 (Box 31)
      - Remedial Action Plan for the City of Ann Arbor Landfill, circa 1992 (Box 31)
      - Request for Proposal for Off-Site Groundwater Feasibility Study/Remedial Action Plan and Submitted Proposals, 1994-1995 (Box 31)
    - Solid Waste Management
      - Ann Arbor Solid Waste Commission
        (Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Proposals, Reports, etc.)
        - 1993-1994 (Box 32)
        - 1995-1996 (Box 32)
      - City of Ann Arbor Integrated Solid Waste Management Plan Update 1994 -- 2000 (Box 32)
      - Commercial Recycling Expansion and Implementation Plan, 2002 (Box 32)
      - Disposing of Commercial and Household Trash: A Survey of Opinions and Behavior Patterns of Washtenaw County Residents and Commercial Establishments, 1988 (Box 32)
      - Proposal Number 389: The City of Ann Arbor, Michigan Solid Waste Collection Services -- Residential -- Commercial -- Multi-Family, 1996 (Box 32)
      - Washtenaw County Act 641 Solid Waste Management Plan Update of 1989, 1990 (Box 32)
      - Washtenaw County Solid Waste Management Plan 1999 Update, 2000 (Box 32)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series consists of photographs and videotapes. The photographs are of several activities of the Center, including recycling, the annual Bike-a-Thon, the GM PRISM project team, organic gardening, and the construction of a local park. The videotapes consist of U-Matic and VHS tapes that were produced and collected by the Ecology Center. The videos include master tapes, public service announcements, training videos, educational videos, and recorded events. Included with some of the videos are study guides and viewing guides.
  - Photographs
    - Bikeathon, 1977-1978 (Box 17)
    - GM PRISM (Partnership for Regulatory Innovation and Sustainable Manufacturing) Project Team, 1997 (Box 17)
    - Great Lakes Household Hazardous Waste Disposal Conference, 1985 (Box 17)
    - Jackson Groundwater Festival, 1993 (Box 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Organic Garden, 1973 (Box 17)
    - Park at Main and Huron, 1973 undated (Box 17)
    - Recycle Ann Arbor Groundbreaking, 1982 (Box 17)
    - Recycling
      - Arbor, 1969-1971 (Box 17)
      - Ecology Center Recycling Center, 1971-1973 (Box 17)
      - Mounted display photographs (Box 17)
    - Rites of, Spring 1974 (Box 17)
  - Videotapes, U-matic format
    - "Home Energy Conservation,", 1983; 1 videotapes 14 minutes U-matic format (Box 18)
    - "What Are We Working With,", 1 videotapes 19 minutes U-matic format (Box 18)
    - "Ground Water Video" Camera Master #1 Beach/Landfill, 1990 (Box 18)
    - "Ground Water Video" Camera Master #2 Beach/Landfill, 1990 (Box 18)
    - "Ground Water Video" Camera Master #3 Beach/Landfill, 1990 (Box 18)
    - "Studio Discussion" Tape 8, 1990 (Box 18)
    - "Studio Discussion" Tape 9, 1990 (Box 18)
    - "It's Found Underground" Edited Master, 1991; 1 videotapes 32 minutes U-matic format (Box 18)
    - "Earth Day is Every Day", 1992 (Box 18)
      (30 and 60 second PSA)
    - "Making the Connection: Household Toxics" (Box 18)
      (Master)
  - Videotapes, VHS format
    - "It's Found Underground,", 1991; 1 videotapes 31 minutes VHS (TM) (Box 19)
    - Study Guide for "It's Found Underground" (Box 19)
    - "Making The Connection: A Teacher's Guide to... Household Hazardous Substances and the Classroom,", 1 videotapes VHS (TM) 13:30 min. (Box 19)
    - "Proposal B-The Greenbelt Debate, Michigan Theatre,", 2003 (Box 19)
    - "Toxics Conference" (Box 19)
    - "Recycling in Your Community-Milan,", 1989; 1 tapes 14:22 min. (Box 19)
    - "UAW/Earth Day,", 1990; 1 tapes 8:17 min. (Box 19)
    - "V.E.I. Facilitator Training Video,", 1991 (Box 19)
    - "I.M.M. Facilitator Training Video,", 1992 (Box 19)
    - "Michigan State Board of Education: Pollution Prevention in Schools,", 1992; 1 videotapes 12 minutes VHS (TM) (Box 19)
    - "Teen News Network: Groundwater Update,", 1993; 1 videotapes 13 minutes VHS (TM) (Box 19)
    - Viewer's Guide for "Teen News Network: Groundwater Update" (Box 19)
    - "Environmental Fund for Michigan Workplace Giving Campaign Video,", 1996; 1 tapes 2:15 min. (Box 19)
    - "Recycling is Easy: Make it Second Nature,", 1999; 1 tapes 11:27 min. (Box 19)
    - "GEM PSA", 1 videotapes 1 minutes VHS (TM) (Box 19)
    - "Recovery & Recycling Station-Automotive Application", 1 tapes 12:30 min. (Box 19)
    - Recycling PSAs DNR, 9 PSAs, 1 videotapes 14:20 min. VHS (TM) (Box 19)
    - "What About Waste?", 1 videotapes 13 minutes VHS (TM) (Box 19)
Related Material
A complete collection of Ecology Reports, the general newsletter of the Ecology Center, can be found in the printed works collection of the Bentley Historical Library.